<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- name="GENERATOR" content="github.com/mmarkdown/mmark Mmark Markdown Processor - mmark.miek.nl" -->
<rfc version="3" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-martin-deploying-ipv6-data-center-00" category="info" xml:lang="en" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" indexInclude="true">

<front>
<title abbrev="deploying-ipv6-data-center">Deploying IPv6 in Data Centers</title><seriesInfo value="draft-martin-deploying-ipv6-data-center-00" status="informational" name="Internet-Draft"></seriesInfo>
<author initials="F." surname="Martin" fullname="Franck Martin"><organization>Peachymango.org</organization><address><postal><street></street>
</postal><email>franck@peachymango.org</email>
</address></author><date year="2026" month="June" day="8"></date>
<area>ops</area>
<workgroup>IPv6 Operations</workgroup>
<keyword>IPv6</keyword>
<keyword>data center</keyword>
<keyword>SRE</keyword>
<keyword>software</keyword>
<keyword>operations</keyword>
<keyword>deployment</keyword>

<abstract>
<t>Data center operators are moving toward IPv6-only operation to simplify
addressing, restore end-to-end connectivity, and meet operator and
government timelines. Much published IPv6 guidance targets network engineers;
this document instead addresses <strong>Site Reliability Engineers (SREs)</strong> and
<strong>Software Engineers (SWEs)</strong> who deploy, operate, and debug services in
data centers. It is organized in two parts after IPv6 fundamentals: a
<strong>migration program</strong> (transition strategy and observability) and a
<strong>technical stack</strong> (hardware, provisioning, transport, applications, and
diagnostics). It documents common software and infrastructure gaps and offers
practical deployment patterns aligned with the IPv6 Operations (v6ops) working
group charter.</t>
</abstract>

</front>

<middle>

<section anchor="introduction"><name>Introduction</name>

<section anchor="audience-and-purpose"><name>Audience and Purpose</name>
<t>This document is written for <strong>Site Reliability Engineers (SREs) and Software
Engineers (SWEs)</strong> who run services in data
centers --- not primarily for network engineers designing routing policy.
Network teams still own prefixes, routing, and firewalls, but IPv6
deployment succeeds or fails in application code, configuration management,
monitoring pipelines, and the long tail of enterprise software that assumes
IPv4.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="related-guides"><name>Related Guides</name>
<t>This document focuses on data center SRE and software engineering practice.
Operators and developers may also find these <strong>informative guides</strong> useful
alongside this draft:</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li><xref target="RFC7381"></xref> --- enterprise IPv6 deployment framework (v6ops)</li>
<li><xref target="RFC4038"></xref> --- application aspects of IPv6 transition</li>
<li><xref target="ARCEP-IPV6-GUIDE"></xref> --- enterprise IPv6 rollout guidance from ARCEP (France)</li>
<li><xref target="ARIN-APPS-V6"></xref> --- application and software developer guidance from ARIN</li>
</ul>
<t>They overlap partially with sections here (applications, addressing, operations)
but cover broader enterprise and regional context.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="document-structure"><name>Document Structure</name>
<t>This document uses a <strong>dual-track structure</strong> after <xref target="ipv6-fundamentals"></xref>: <strong>Part I</strong>
defines migration policy and measurement; <strong>Part II</strong> implements the stack from
management hardware upward. Fundamentals establish shared vocabulary for SREs
and software engineers; both parts are required for a complete IPv6-only data
center. Overlapping themes (for example internal vs external scope in
<xref target="internal-external"></xref> and <xref target="provision-not-transform"></xref>) appear where each audience
needs them; sections cross-link rather than repeat editorially.</t>
<t><strong>Part I --- Running the migration:</strong> <xref target="transition"></xref> covers operating model and
scope (greenfield provisioning vs brownfield conversion, IPv6-only jump hosts).
<xref target="observability"></xref> defines inventory schema, dashboards, and success metrics ---
fix what you measure before bulk technical change.</t>
<t><strong>Part II --- Building the IPv6 data center</strong> follows a bottom-up order: <xref target="oob-management"></xref>
(hardware and management plane), <xref target="internet-addressing"></xref> and <xref target="dns-registration"></xref>
(provisioning), <xref target="icmpv6-pmtud"></xref> (transport health), then application work ---
<xref target="application-readiness"></xref>, <xref target="name-resolution"></xref>, <xref target="client-load-balancing"></xref> --- and
<xref target="network-diagnostics"></xref> for production troubleshooting.</t>
<t><strong>Reading paths by role:</strong></t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li><em>Program lead / engineering manager:</em> Part I first, then Part II as overview.</li>
<li><em>Network / DC infrastructure engineer:</em> <xref target="ipv6-fundamentals"></xref>, then Part II
sections on OOB through ICMPv6/PMTUD.</li>
<li><em>Application / SRE engineer:</em> <xref target="ipv6-fundamentals"></xref>, Part I <xref target="observability"></xref>,
then Part II application and diagnostics sections.</li>
<li><em>Full migration owner:</em> linear --- fundamentals, Part I, Part II, then
Security Considerations.</li>
</ul>
</section>

<section anchor="requirements-language"><name>Requirements Language</name>
<t>The key words &quot;<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>&quot;, &quot;<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>&quot;, &quot;<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>&quot;, &quot;<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>&quot;,
&quot;<bcp14>SHALL NOT</bcp14>&quot;, &quot;<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>&quot;, &quot;<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>&quot;, &quot;<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>&quot;,
&quot;<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>&quot;, &quot;<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>&quot;, and &quot;<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>&quot; in this document are to
be interpreted as described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"></xref> <xref target="RFC8174"></xref> when, and only
when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="ipv6-fundamentals"><name>IPv6 Fundamentals for Software Engineers</name>
<t>Software engineers who have worked only in IPv4 environments often discover
that IPv6 is not &quot;IPv4 with longer addresses.&quot; The differences below affect
code, configuration, monitoring, and troubleshooting daily.</t>

<section anchor="address-size-and-header-format"><name>Address Size and Header Format</name>
<t>IPv4 addresses are <strong>32 bits</strong>; IPv6 addresses are <strong>128 bits</strong>
<xref target="RFC8200"></xref>. The IPv4 header has a <strong>variable length</strong> because options are
carried in the main header. The IPv6 header has a <strong>fixed 40-byte length</strong>,
which simplifies fast-path processing on routers and hosts. Additional IPv6
options live in <strong>extension headers</strong> chained after the main header; routers
<strong>do not need to process</strong> most extension headers for forwarding
<xref target="RFC8200"></xref>.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="checksums-jumbo-frames-and-fragmentation"><name>Checksums, Jumbo Frames, and Fragmentation</name>
<t>IPv6 removed the header checksum present in IPv4; integrity is assumed to be
covered by upper-layer protocols (for example, TCP, UDP, and SCTP) and link
layers where applicable <xref target="RFC8200"></xref>. Operators can use <strong>jumbo frames</strong> on
supported paths to reduce per-packet overhead and acknowledgment rates on
high-throughput links. Jumbo frames are an operational choice on the LAN and
require end-to-end support; they are not an IPv6 requirement but are often
easier to reason about once NAT middleboxes are removed.</t>
<t>IPv4 allowed routers to fragment packets in transit. IPv6 <strong>fragments only at
endpoints</strong> <xref target="RFC8200"></xref>. If a packet exceeds the path MTU, the source discovers
the limit through Path MTU Discovery (see <xref target="icmpv6-pmtud"></xref>) rather than relying
on router fragmentation. Application teams that tune MSS or disable PMTUD on
IPv4 must not copy those habits blindly to IPv6.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="icmpv6-and-neighbor-discovery"><name>ICMPv6 and Neighbor Discovery</name>
<t>IPv4 Address Resolution Protocol (ARP) is replaced in IPv6 by <strong>Neighbor
Discovery (ND)</strong> carried in <strong>ICMPv6</strong> <xref target="RFC4861"></xref> <xref target="RFC4443"></xref>. ND resolves
addresses on the local link, discovers routers, and performs other essential
functions. <strong>ICMPv6 therefore MUST NOT be blocked wholesale</strong> on IPv6 paths
the way some IPv4 deployments block all ICMP. Blocking ICMPv6 breaks ND and
PMTUD and produces failures that look like application bugs.  Guidance exists
to identify essential ICMPv6 traffic that should not be blocked <xref target="RFC4890"></xref>.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="end-to-end-connectivity"><name>End-to-End Connectivity</name>
<t>IPv4 data centers often rely on Network Address Translation (NAT), carrier-grade
NAT (CGNAT), and overlapping private address space <xref target="RFC1918"></xref>. IPv6 restores
the <strong>end-to-end principle</strong>: globally unique addresses (with deliberate
exceptions noted below) can be routed on the Internet without translation.
Routing replaces NAT for many multi-tenant container scenarios, which simplifies
traffic inspection but requires disciplined prefix planning (see
<xref target="internet-addressing"></xref>).</t>
</section>

<section anchor="address-types"><name>Address Types and Terminology</name>
<t>Careless use of the word &quot;IPv6&quot; causes outages. This document uses the
following terms:</t>
<t><strong>Link-local address</strong>: An address in <tt>fe80::/10</tt> used only on a single link
<xref target="RFC4291"></xref>. Link-local addresses are <strong>not</strong> routed on the Internet. On
Linux, connecting to a link-local destination requires a <strong>zone identifier</strong>
(for example, <tt>fe80::1%eth0</tt>) because the same link-local prefix exists on
every interface.</t>
<t><strong>Unique Local Address (ULA)</strong>: An address in <tt>fc00::/7</tt> intended for local
use and <strong>not</strong> globally routed <xref target="RFC4193"></xref>. ULAs resemble IPv4 private space
in purpose but are uncommon in many data center designs that use provider-
aggregated global unicast space internally. Like IPv4 private address space,
ULAs can create <strong>renumbering work</strong> when companies merge or networks are
combined --- a data center network is never final.</t>
<t><strong>Global Unicast Address (GUA)</strong>: A globally routable IPv6 address assigned
from an organization's allocation of IPv6 addresses.</t>
<t>Unlike IPv4, there is <strong>no RFC 1918 equivalent that dominates data center
design</strong>. With rare exceptions (link-local, ULA, and special-purpose ranges
in <xref target="RFC6890"></xref>), <strong>IPv6 unicast addresses are designed to be globally
unique and routable</strong>. Security boundaries are enforced by routing policy and
firewall rules, not by assuming addresses are inherently non-routable.  We
use two additional terms to distinguish addresses based on thes policies:</t>
<t><strong>Internal global unicast address</strong>: A globally routable IPv6 address used
<strong>inside</strong> the data center.  These addresses are reachable according to
routing and security policy, not because they are &quot;private.&quot;</t>
<t><strong>External global unicast address</strong>: A globally routable address presented to
clients on the Internet, often via load balancers or anycast.</t>
<t>Unlike IPv4, nodes typically have multiple IPv6 addresses assigned to each
of their interfaces.  The link-local addresses are necessary to participate
in Neighbor Discovery and so serve a vital purpose even though they are not
globally routable.  Additionally, because so many IPv6 addresses are
available, some machines may use multiple global addresses simultaneously
for purposes such as privacy or temporary use.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="address-representation"><name>Address Representation</name>
<t>IPv6 addresses have several equivalent textual forms <xref target="RFC4291"></xref>:</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li>Full form: <tt>2001:db8:0:0:0:0:0:1</tt></li>
<li>Compressed zeros: <tt>2001:db8::1</tt></li>
<li>Loopback: <tt>::1</tt> (compare IPv4 <tt>127.0.0.1</tt>)</li>
<li>Unspecified: <tt>::</tt></li>
<li>IPv4-mapped IPv6: <tt>::ffff:192.0.2.1</tt></li>
</ul>
<t>In <strong>dual-stack</strong> environments, IPv4 addresses also appear in multiple forms
in code and configuration:</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li>Dotted decimal: <tt>192.0.2.1</tt></li>
<li>Integer (historical APIs): <tt>3232235521</tt></li>
<li>Hex packed in configs: <tt>0xC0000201</tt></li>
<li>Mapped in IPv6 APIs: <tt>::ffff:192.0.2.1</tt></li>
</ul>
<t>In software, addresses <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be stored in a <strong>binary field or structure
sized for 128 bits</strong> (for example, <tt>in6_addr</tt>, <tt>sockaddr_storage</tt>, or an
equivalent language type), so the same field can hold IPv4 or IPv6. <strong>Do not
store addresses as strings</strong> in databases, logs-as-data, caches, or message
payloads. Provide helper functions to convert between the binary form and a
human-readable representation for display and configuration I/O, and use those
helpers at boundaries --- <strong>never parse or compare address strings ad hoc</strong> in
application logic.</t>
<t>Applications <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> treat names, not literal addresses, as the stable
interface (see <xref target="naming-services"></xref>). To turn a name into addresses, use the
APIs described in <xref target="name-resolution"></xref> --- not legacy one-address helpers and
not string parsing.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="prefix-length-and-the-64-convention"><name>Prefix Length and the /64 Convention</name>
<t>On most LANs and data center segments, the <strong>network/host split is at the
64th bit</strong> --- a <tt>/64</tt> prefix on the wire <xref target="RFC4291"></xref>. Roughly speaking, a
<tt>/64</tt> is the IPv6 analogue of an IPv4 <tt>/24</tt> in terms of &quot;one subnet per
broadcast domain,&quot; though the address space is vastly larger. A good data
center pattern assigns a <strong><tt>/56</tt> per host</strong> so each container can receive its
own <strong><tt>/64</tt></strong> (see <xref target="prefix-allocation"></xref>).</t>
</section>

<section anchor="link-local-gateways"><name>Link-Local Gateways</name>
<t>A good practice is to place the default gateway at <strong><tt>fe80::1</tt></strong> on each
link. That choice avoids consuming a global address for the router and matches
common vendor examples. Servers <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> specify the outgoing interface when
using link-local next hops (for example, <tt>ip -6 route add default via fe80::1
dev eth0</tt>). The router platform <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> actually configure <tt>fe80::1</tt> on the
expected interface.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="naming-services"><name>Naming Services</name>
<t><tt>::1</tt> is <tt>localhost</tt>; <tt>127.0.0.1</tt> is <tt>localhost</tt>. <strong>Do not embed IP addresses
in application code</strong> when a name will do. Use hostnames and service discovery;
resolve names at connection time.</t>
<t>DNS (or an equivalent naming and service registry) becomes <strong>essential</strong> in
IPv6 because humans cannot memorize 128-bit addresses. Operational maturity
includes forward and reverse DNS for infrastructure, health checks keyed on
names, and monitoring that labels series by hostname rather than by address
literals.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="part-i-running-the-migration"><name>Part I: Running the Migration</name>
</section>

<section anchor="transition"><name>Transition Strategies</name>

<section anchor="provision-not-transform"><name>Easier to Provision Than to Transform</name>
<t><strong>It is easier to provision IPv6 correctly than to transform a running service.</strong>
Enabling dual-stack or IPv6-only on a server, container, or service that was
deployed IPv4-only means changing addresses, ACLs, DNS, health checks, and
often application configuration --- then <strong>restarting in place</strong> and hoping
nothing was missed. Provisioning time already runs those checks, supports
canary or phased ramp-up, and catches failures before the service takes
production traffic.</t>
<t>Teams <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> treat every <strong>new service</strong>, <strong>new software version</strong>, and
<strong>rewrite of an existing application</strong> as an opportunity to ship <strong>IPv6-only on
internal interfaces</strong> from the start (see <xref target="internal-external"></xref>), with <strong>dual-stack
only where external reachability requires it</strong>, rather than cloning an IPv4-only
template and scheduling conversion later. Brownfield conversion remains necessary
for legacy estates, but the default for greenfield work <bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14> be
&quot;IPv4 now, IPv6 someday.&quot;</t>
</section>

<section anchor="ipv6-only-jump-hosts"><name>IPv6-Only Jump Hosts</name>
<t>Moving to IPv6 is not only a routing change --- it requires a <strong>cultural shift</strong>
for SREs and SWEs who have spent years assuming IPv4 literals, RFC 1918 mental
models, and IPv4-first tooling. <strong>Make that shift visible before emergencies:</strong>
IPv6-only jump hosts, IPv6-first runbooks, and labeled lab networks teach the
new defaults while change windows are calm. Engineers under incident pressure
<strong>do not have time to learn IPv6 idioms</strong>; if the first time they need <tt>dig -x</tt>
on an <tt>ip6.arpa</tt> name or SSH over a global v6 management address is during a
sev-1, the organization has already failed the migration program.</t>
<t>A practical staged transition puts <strong>administrative jump hosts on IPv6-only</strong>
access while leaving application tiers dual-stack temporarily. Engineers run
configuration management, monitoring CLI tools, and break-glass SSH from those
hosts, forcing administrative tooling onto IPv6. Maintain at least one
<strong>dual-stack backup jump host</strong> during migration and <strong>audit who connects and
which commands run</strong> until parity is proven.</t>
<t>Temporarily <strong>reducing IPv4 SSH session timeouts</strong> on jump hosts can accelerate
detection of accidental IPv4 dependency without blocking emergency access.</t>
<t>Apply the same staged exposure to <strong>corporate wireless</strong>, not only SSH bastions.
Provide <strong>dual-stack Wi-Fi</strong> for everyday employee devices during migration, and
at least one <strong>IPv6-only employee Wi-Fi</strong> SSID so laptops, phones, VPN clients,
and captive-portal flows are exercised on AAAA-only paths before production
depends on them. Label SSIDs explicitly (for example, <tt>corp-dualstack</tt> and
<tt>corp-v6-only</tt>) so engineers know which network they joined.</t>
<t>Some operators <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> additionally offer <strong>IPv6-only guest Wi-Fi</strong> --- for
example in lab, conference, or vendor demo areas --- so external teams can
demonstrate that hardware and software work without IPv4 fallback during
evaluations and acceptance testing. That network <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be clearly marked,
rate-limited, and isolated from internal management zones; it complements jump
hosts but does not replace them for break-glass administration.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="observability"><name>Observability and Metrics</name>
<t>IPv6 migration needs <strong>inventory plus measurement</strong>: a service list with IPv6
readiness labels, automated discovery of what is missing from that list, and
time-series metrics that show progress toward dual-stack or IPv6-only targets.</t>

<section anchor="service-inventory-and-discovery"><name>Service Inventory and Discovery</name>
<t>The inventory in <xref target="application-readiness"></xref> <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> list every application and
platform component with a readiness state (for example: IPv6-only ready,
dual-stack, IPv4-only, unknown). Inventory alone is not enough --- operators
<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> run periodic <strong>discovery</strong> that compares running processes, container
images, load balancer pools, and DNS names against the catalog and <strong>flags
unregistered services</strong>. Shadow deployments and shared hosts routinely run
software that no team has classified.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="progress-metrics"><name>Progress Metrics</name>
<t>Dashboards <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> expose fleet-level indicators, for example:</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li>Percentage of services <strong>IPv6-only</strong>, <strong>dual-stack</strong>, or <strong>IPv4-only</strong> (by
count and by criticality tier)</li>
<li>Trend of <strong>AAAA vs A-only</strong> DNS names for production hostnames</li>
<li>Ratio of <strong>ingress bytes or connections</strong> over IPv6 vs IPv4 at load balancers</li>
<li>Count of hosts or pods <strong>without any IPv6 address</strong> in IPAM or configuration
management</li>
</ul>
<t>Set explicit targets (for example, &quot;90% of tier-1 APIs dual-stack by Q4&quot;) and
review the same metrics in change advisory boards.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="dual-stack-regression-and-hard-failures-on-ipv6"><name>Dual-Stack Regression and Hard Failures on IPv6</name>
<t>Dual-stack is a valuable migration step, but <strong>without monitoring it invites
regression</strong>. A service that passed dual-stack testing can <strong>stop working on IPv6</strong>
after an unrelated code push --- for example, a new dependency, a changed bind
address, or a refactored HTTP client that silently prefers IPv4. Unmonitored
dual-stack fleets often <strong>mask</strong> such regressions because IPv4 still succeeds.</t>
<t><strong>Treat IPv6 failures as hard failures as soon as policy allows</strong> --- alert on
IPv6-only health checks, IPv6 listen-socket regressions, and rising IPv4-only
connection share for tier-1 services. Where production remains dual-stack,
synthetic probes <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> exercise <strong>IPv6 explicitly</strong> (AAAA-only paths,
IPv6 literal targets, or IPv6-only test clients), not only dual-stack clients
that can hide breakage. The sooner IPv6 errors page on-call the same way IPv4
errors do, the less likely a team discovers IPv6 rot months later during an
IPv4 decommissioning drill.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="host-level-listen-socket-audit"><name>Host-Level Listen-Socket Audit</name>
<t>On each host, collect which services <strong>listen on IPv4-only</strong>, <strong>IPv6-only</strong>, or
<strong>dual-stack</strong>. On Linux, <tt>ss -tulnp</tt> (or <tt>/proc/net/tcp</tt> and <tt>tcp6</tt>) is the
usual source, but classification is <strong>non-trivial</strong>:</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li>Separate <tt>tcp</tt>/<tt>udp</tt> vs <tt>tcp6</tt>/<tt>udp6</tt> lines are often <strong>IPv4-only</strong> vs
<strong>IPv6-only</strong> listeners.</li>
<li>A single IPv6 socket with <tt>IPV6_V6ONLY=0</tt> may accept IPv4-mapped traffic
without a matching <tt>tcp</tt> line --- treat as <strong>dual-stack</strong> only after checking
socket options or process documentation.</li>
<li>Match rows by <strong>PID, port, and inode</strong> when correlating multiple lines for one
daemon; export a normalized label (<tt>v4-only</tt>, <tt>v6-only</tt>, <tt>dual-stack</tt>,
<tt>unknown</tt>) for metrics.</li>
</ul>
<t>Run this audit on a schedule and on every deploy; alert when a tier-1 service
regresses to IPv4-only.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="host-agents"><name>Host Agents Before Application Provisioning</name>
<t>Before any application software is installed, <strong>inventory every agent and
daemon already running on the host</strong> --- configuration management, monitoring,
log shippers, vulnerability scanners, <strong>EDR</strong>, host firewalls, and other
platform packages the fleet image includes by default. These components often
<strong>bind IPv4-only</strong>, ship IPv4-only policy from a central console, or break when
the host loses IPv4 even if the workload you plan to deploy is IPv6-ready.</t>
<t>Run this baseline check on <strong>golden images and freshly provisioned servers</strong>, not
only on production services. A host cannot safely move to dual-stack or
IPv6-only if an unknown agent still requires IPv4 loopback, RFC 1918 reachability,
or IPv4-only reporting to its controller. Export agent name, version, listen
sockets (see above), and <strong>IPv6 readiness</strong> into the same catalog as
<xref target="application-readiness"></xref>. Re-run when the image or security baseline changes.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="traffic-by-protocol-and-address-family"><name>Traffic by Protocol and Address Family</name>
<t>Switches and routers expose <strong>IPv4 and IPv6 packet counters</strong> but often <strong>do
not break out TCP and UDP by IP version</strong> (TCPv4 vs TCPv6, UDPv4 vs UDPv6).
Where the platform allows, collect <strong><tt>tcp4</tt>/<tt>udp4</tt> vs <tt>tcp6</tt>/<tt>udp6</tt></strong> (or
equivalent flow records) on hosts, hypervisors, and top-of-rack devices.
Application SREs need <strong>L4 metrics split by address family</strong> to confirm traffic
is migrating and to find stragglers still on IPv4-only or translated paths.</t>
<t>Log pipelines <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> record address family explicitly (<tt>AF_INET</tt> vs
<tt>AF_INET6</tt>) rather than inferring from string shape.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="http-signaling-and-planned-ipv4-drills"><name>HTTP Signaling and Planned IPv4 Drills</name>
<t>For HTTP services, implementing <eref target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-martin-retry-over-ipv6/">HTTP Signaling of Planned IPv4
Unavailability</eref>
(<tt>566</tt> responses, <tt>Retry-Over-IPv6</tt>, and related headers) gives <strong>measurable
signals</strong> during planned IPv4 outages: count <tt>566</tt> responses, soft vs hard
failures after IPv6 retry, and clients still hitting IPv4. That data belongs on
the same dashboards as listen-socket and byte-ratio metrics when rolling out
dual-stack or IPv6-only frontends.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="live-traffic-and-service-call-trees"><name>Live Traffic and Service Call Trees</name>
<t>Inventory and socket audits show <strong>what could</strong> run on IPv6; live traffic shows
<strong>what does</strong>. Instrument outbound and inbound connections (service mesh,
eBPF, proxy access logs, or APM) to tag each hop with <strong>address family</strong>.
Roll those tags into a <strong>call tree or dependency graph per service</strong> so teams
see, for example, &quot;API gateway is dual-stack but 80% of backend calls still use
IPv4&quot; or &quot;this batch job is IPv4-only despite an IPv6-ready binary.&quot;</t>
<t>Use call-tree family breakdown to prioritize refactors: fix the highest-volume
IPv4-only edges first. Reconcile call-tree findings with the inventory --- a
service marked &quot;IPv6 ready&quot; with no IPv6 traffic is not done.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="part-ii-building-the-ipv6-data-center"><name>Part II: Building the IPv6 Data Center</name>
</section>

<section anchor="oob-management"><name>Out-of-Band Management and Network Boot</name>
<t>Software readiness is insufficient if servers cannot be <strong>installed, booted, or
power-cycled</strong> over IPv6. This area <strong>SHOULD be tackled very early</strong> in an IPv6
program --- before application tiers --- because <strong>hardware refresh cycles can
take up to five years</strong>. A server bought today with an IPv4-only baseboard
management controller (BMC) or provisioning stack may still block IPv6-only
operation long after application code is ready.</t>

<section anchor="often-forgotten-infrastructure-devices"><name>Often-Forgotten Infrastructure Devices</name>
<t>Out-of-band work is not limited to compute <strong>IPMI</strong>, <strong>Redfish</strong>, and <strong>PXE</strong>.
Teams routinely overlook <strong>facility and operations gear</strong> that shares the same
management VLANs and must be reachable during incidents:</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li><strong>UPS</strong> and power distribution monitoring</li>
<li><strong>Climate control</strong> (CRAC, chillers, environmental sensors)</li>
<li><strong>NTP</strong> appliances or stratum servers on dedicated hardware</li>
<li><strong>Console servers</strong> and serial concentrators</li>
<li><strong>KVM switches</strong>, rack PDUs, and other <strong>data center infrastructure
management</strong> devices</li>
</ul>
<t>These systems often ship with <strong>fixed IPv4-only interfaces</strong>, embedded web UIs
bound to <tt>192.168.x.x</tt>, and long firmware cadences. Include them in the same
IPv6 readiness inventory as production servers (see <xref target="application-readiness"></xref> and
<xref target="observability"></xref>); they become blockers during IPv4 decommissioning even when
every application pod is dual-stack.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="firmware-and-pxe-uefi-boot"><name>Firmware and PXE/UEFI Boot</name>
<t>Many <strong>BIOS</strong> implementations still lack usable IPv6. <strong>UEFI network boot</strong>
over IPv6 exists but <strong>varies by server vendor</strong> in ways that affect
automated provisioning. Network appliance <strong>EFI</strong> implementations are similarly
inconsistent. An IPv6-only provisioning VLAN requires explicit qualification of
every hardware generation in the fleet.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="ipmi-and-redfish"><name>IPMI and Redfish</name>
<t><strong>IPMI over IPv6</strong> is <strong>essential</strong> for <strong>remote power cycle and reboot</strong> when
management networks move to IPv6-only. Without a working BMC address on v6,
automation cannot recover a hung host without a physical visit. The same
requirement applies to the <strong>provisioning and reboot toolchain</strong> --- imaging,
PXE/UEFI orchestration, configuration management kickstart, and out-of-band
serial concentrators <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be <strong>dual-stack or IPv6-only capable</strong> before
internal management VLANs drop IPv4.</t>
<t><strong>IPMI</strong> and <strong>Redfish</strong> IPv6 support differs by vendor and firmware generation:
some platforms support SLAAC, others DHCPv6, others require initial IPv4
configuration before enabling IPv6. Linux <tt>ipmitool</tt> subcommands and output
formats vary with firmware. Enterprises often <strong>defer firmware upgrades</strong> because
failed BMC updates require physical data center visits --- plan IPv6 on management
networks with spare in-rack capacity and conservative change windows.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="internet-addressing"><name>Internet and Data Center Addressing</name>
<t>Network teams assign prefixes; SREs consume them in orchestration templates,
container runtimes, and firewall tickets. This section covers patterns that
reduce outages during rollout.</t>

<section anchor="prefix-allocation"><name>Prefix Allocation for Hosts and Containers</name>
<t>A common data center pattern assigns a <strong><tt>/56</tt> to each physical host</strong> (or
rack entity), providing <strong>256 <tt>/64</tt> subnets</strong> --- one <tt>/64</tt> for the host itself
and up to <strong>255 <tt>/64</tt> prefixes</strong> for containers, virtual machines, or
Kubernetes pods. Each container <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> receive a full <strong><tt>/64</tt></strong>, not a
longer prefix carved out of a single host <tt>/64</tt>. Routing between <tt>/64</tt> islands
replaces NAT for east-west traffic and avoids CGNAT-style visibility loss in
flow logs. Assigning only a <strong><tt>/64</tt> per host</strong> (or per rack entity without
further delegation) is <strong>often insufficient</strong> when multiple containers each
need their own address space; request a <strong><tt>/56</tt> (or shorter)</strong> delegation from
the network team instead. In a <strong>closed data center</strong> with explicit routing and
no SLAAC on container segments, some designs assign one <strong><tt>/64</tt> per physical
host</strong> and carve <strong><tt>/72</tt> (or longer) subnets</strong> from that host prefix for
container tiers. That pattern is <strong>not</strong> suitable on the public Internet or
where hosts expect standard <tt>/64</tt> semantics; use it only with operator-wide
agreement and tested CNI or orchestrator support.</t>
<t>The exact mapping depends on orchestrator and CNI design; the important software
lesson is that <strong>each tier needs an explicit prefix plan</strong> rather than assuming
&quot;one address per host&quot; as in legacy IPv4 NAT designs.</t>
<t>Kubernetes clusters often use eBPF-based service NAT on the node. Traditional
Linux tools (<tt>ss</tt>, <tt>/proc/net/tcp</tt>) may show node-level sockets, not pod-level
flows, when NAT is involved. IPv6 routing reduces NAT use --- which also
<strong>reduces the complexity inherent in NAT when tracing connections</strong> --- but
<strong>does not remove the need for observability hooks</strong> at the CNI layer.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="static-addressing-router-advertisements-and-ipam"><name>Static Addressing, Router Advertisements, and IPAM</name>
<t>Enterprise data centers usually prefer <strong>static addresses</strong> from an IP Address
Management (IPAM) system over SLAAC-derived random interface identifiers.
Disable <strong>Router Advertisements (RA)</strong> on server-facing <strong>switch ports</strong> (for
example by clearing the <strong>Managed</strong> and <strong>Other</strong> flags) <strong>and</strong> disable
<strong>SLAAC</strong> on <strong>servers and other endpoints</strong> when static addressing is required.
Applying both controls --- at the <strong>network edge and on the host</strong> --- provides
<strong>two layers of protection</strong> so hosts do not acquire unexpected addresses
alongside provisioned ones.</t>
<t>Gateway at <strong><tt>fe80::1</tt></strong>, global addresses from IPAM, and DNS names registered
in forward and reverse zones should be one coordinated change set.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="semantic-prefixes"><name>Semantic Prefixes for Internal Traffic</name>
<t>On IPv4, operators quickly tell <strong>internal from Internet</strong> traffic: RFC 1918
space such as <tt>10.0.0.0/8</tt> and <tt>192.168.0.0/16</tt> signals &quot;inside the
organization&quot; in logs, captures, and mental models <xref target="RFC1918"></xref>. On IPv6, most
data center addresses are <strong>global unicast</strong> --- there is no automatic &quot;private
vs public&quot; heuristic. Debugging and ACL writing become harder unless the site
<strong>designates a small set of well-known aggregates</strong> in IPAM and teaches SREs to
use them.</t>
<t>A practical pattern is to carve <strong>one prefix for each operational class</strong>, for
example:</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li><strong>Everything in the data center</strong> --- one aggregated prefix (the exact length
depends on fleet size; a <tt>/26</tt> under the site GUA is an example when the
block is purely semantic and routing summarizes wider internally)</li>
<li><strong>Everything employees</strong> --- corporate VPN, office wired/wireless for staff</li>
<li><strong>Everything guest Wi-Fi</strong> --- captive portal and untrusted clients</li>
</ul>
<t>SREs then remember <strong>three networks</strong>, not hundreds of <tt>/64</tt>s, when filtering
pcaps, writing runbooks, or explaining an incident. Document these prefixes in
the same place as <xref target="prefix-allocation"></xref> and <xref target="acl-propagation"></xref> rules so logs,
firewall objects, and monitoring use consistent names (<tt>dc-internal</tt>,
<tt>corp-employee</tt>, <tt>guest-wifi</tt>).</t>
<t><strong>Internal data center prefixes SHOULD NOT be announced or routed to the
Internet.</strong> Even when addresses are global unicast, <strong>BGP and routing policy</strong>
at the edge <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> filter site-internal aggregates so they remain reachable
only inside the operator network. That routing boundary adds <strong>defense in depth</strong>
on top of firewalls: a misconfigured ACL or leaked route is less likely to expose
internal infrastructure to the public Internet.</t>
<t>Monitoring, security analytics, and log UIs <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> let operators <strong>assign
visible colors or tags to semantic prefix ranges</strong> --- for example, external
(Internet-facing) addresses in one color, data center internal prefixes in
another, and corporate or employee VPN ranges in a third. The exact palette is
operator choice; the goal is instant recognition in dashboards, alerts, and
pcap summaries without parsing every <tt>/64</tt>.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="internet-egress"><name>Internet Egress and Edge Gateways</name>
<t>On IPv4 it is often convenient to give a data center host Internet access via
<strong>NAT44</strong> (or operator CGNAT) on a central device. That pattern <strong>SHOULD NOT
be copied onto IPv6 hosts</strong> --- do not deploy ad hoc <strong>NAT66</strong> or per-server
masquerading so internal servers &quot;hide&quot; behind random IPv6 ports. Internal
hosts <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> reach the Internet through a <strong>gateway at the edge</strong> (border
router, firewall, or dedicated translation cluster) with explicit policy and
logging.</t>
<t>That edge model still helps when an <strong>IPv6-only server</strong> must reach an
<strong>IPv4-only Internet service</strong>: the server sends IPv6 to the edge; the gateway
performs <strong>NAT64</strong> or protocol translation <xref target="RFC6146"></xref> (and DNS64 where
needed) on the way out. Translation is <strong>centralized, observable, and
rate-limited</strong> --- not duplicated on every app host.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="internal-external"><name>Internal vs External: Where IPv6-Only Applies</name>
<t>A practical <strong>IPv6-only data center</strong> usually means <strong>IPv6-only on internal
interfaces and east-west paths</strong>, not on every interface facing the outside
world. The <strong>Internet is not yet ready for an IPv6-only-only edge</strong>: clients,
transit, partners, and operator tooling still expect <strong>dual-stack</strong> (or IPv4
fallback) on <strong>external</strong> interfaces --- load balancers, border routers, VPN
concentrators, and customer-facing anycast fronts.</t>
<t>Plan accordingly:</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li><strong>Inside the data center:</strong> servers, containers, and service-to-service traffic
<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> move to <strong>IPv6-only</strong> (or IPv6-primary) on internal VLANs and
<tt>/64</tt> islands as readiness allows.</li>
<li><strong>At the edge:</strong> <strong>external interfaces SHOULD remain dual-stack</strong> until IPv4
dependency is gone for your user base and upstream paths. The edge gateway
performs translation when an internal IPv6-only host must reach IPv4-only
destinations (see above).</li>
</ul>
<t><strong>Dual-home servers on the edge</strong> --- one <strong>internal</strong> interface (IPv6-only or
IPv6-primary) and one <strong>external</strong> interface (dual-stack) --- simplify
<strong>administration and break-glass access</strong>: operators and automation can reach
management paths on the internal v6 network while the service still serves
dual-stack Internet clients. Document which interface is which in IPAM and
host naming; do not collapse &quot;internal v6-only&quot; and &quot;external dual-stack&quot; into
a single ambiguous address on production boxes.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="ipv4-only-wrappers"><name>Frontends for IPv4-Only Services</name>
<t>Legacy applications that remain <strong>IPv4-only</strong> <bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14> be exposed
directly to dual-stack or IPv6-only clients. Surround them with a <strong>gateway
tier</strong> --- for example <strong>nginx</strong>, <strong>HAProxy</strong>, or a service-mesh ingress ---
that accepts <strong>IPv6 (and IPv4 if required)</strong> on the front side and speaks IPv4
only to the backend. Clients see a normal v6-capable service name; the
IPv4-only binary stays on an internal path until it is rewritten or replaced
(see <xref target="provision-not-transform"></xref>).</t>
<t>An alternative on the host is <strong>NAT64 implemented with eBPF</strong> (similar in spirit
to Kubernetes node NAT). That can unblock a single service quickly but <strong>often
does not scale</strong> as a fleet-wide strategy --- connection state, troubleshooting,
and upgrade churn multiply with every host doing translation. Prefer a <strong>small
number of shared frontends or edge translators</strong> over per-host NAT64 except in
controlled exceptions. See also <xref target="icmpv6-pmtud"></xref> for VPN and middlebox
interactions with translated traffic.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="acl-propagation"><name>Access Control List Propagation</name>
<t>When IPv6 is added to a service that already runs on IPv4, <strong>firewall and ACL
automation may lag by minutes</strong>. During that window the service can appear
<strong>healthy on IPv4 but broken on IPv6</strong>, or reachable in one direction only.
SRE runbooks <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> treat &quot;IPv6 enabled on the host&quot; and &quot;IPv6 permitted
end-to-end&quot; as separate checklist items. Do not announce IPv6 on a load
balancer until policy propagation completes.</t>
<t>Software teams <bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14> create entirely new ACL models per address family
when the same role-based policy can express both; parallel rule sets double
drift risk. Where separate rules are unavoidable, generate them from the same
source of truth.</t>

<section anchor="ipam-based-ipv4-to-ipv6-mapping-for-acls"><name>IPAM-Based IPv4-to-IPv6 Mapping for ACLs</name>
<t>When IPAM tracks both address families, operators can <strong>derive a predictable
IPv6 address from a hostname</strong> before an AAAA record exists in DNS. That
mapping lets ACL and firewall systems publish <strong>IPv6 rules in advance</strong>, so
policy is already in place when the service starts listening on IPv6 --- there
is no window where the host is up on IPv6 but ACL automation is still catching
up.</t>
<t>This pattern <strong>requires ACL policy to be expressed by hostname (or role)</strong>, not
by scattered literal addresses maintained separately per family. Given a hostname,
a controller can resolve or derive addresses with the following <strong>pseudo-rules</strong>:</t>

<ol spacing="compact">
<li>Look up the <strong>AAAA</strong> record. If present, use that IPv6 address.</li>
<li>If no AAAA exists, look up the <strong>A</strong> record and obtain the IPv4 address.</li>
<li>In IPAM, find the <strong>IPv4 network</strong> that contains that address.</li>
<li>Find the <strong>associated IPv6 network</strong> paired with that IPv4 network in IPAM.</li>
<li><strong>Embed the IPv4 address</strong> into the IPv6 network according to the site's
translation plan (for example, a fixed nibble layout or well-known offset).
The result is the <strong>predicted IPv6 address</strong> for that hostname.</li>
</ol>
<t>The benefit is operational: <strong>ACLs for IPv6 can be built and deployed everywhere
before DNS advertises AAAA</strong>, because the IPv6 address is computable from the
same hostname and IPAM data already used for IPv4. When the service later
enables IPv6 and the AAAA is published, the pre-provisioned rules should match
without a second ACL rollout. The site translation plan in step 5 <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be
documented and stable; ad hoc embedding layouts defeat this approach.</t>
<t>The same correlation policy supports an <strong>early dual-stack step on the host</strong>
without advertising <strong>AAAA</strong> in DNS. IPAM assigns the predicted IPv6 address on
the interface; the application tier can remain <strong>IPv4-only</strong> (A record only,
IPv4 listen sockets) while <strong>outbound</strong> traffic from the host uses IPv6. That
lets platform agents --- configuration management, monitoring, log shippers,
vulnerability scanners, and other infrastructure daemons (see <xref target="host-agents"></xref>)
--- reach <strong>IPv6-only</strong> services on the fabric before application code is
ready. Inbound clients still use IPv4 until a deliberate cutover adds AAAA and
dual-stack or IPv6-only listeners; pre-provision ACLs and routing for the
predicted v6 address using the steps above.</t>
<t>If ACL systems cannot accept hostnames and expand them through this logic,
teams fall back to the lag problem described above --- IPv6 goes live while
firewall tickets are still in flight.</t>
</section>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="dns-registration"><name>DNS Registration and Dynamic Addressing</name>
<t>IPv6's default autoconfiguration (SLAAC) generates addresses from interface
identifiers. Without operational discipline, <strong>DNS lags behind actual
addresses</strong>, and break-glass access by name fails.</t>

<section anchor="slaac-switches-and-the-dns-gap"><name>SLAAC, Switches, and the DNS Gap</name>
<t>Wi-Fi controllers often integrate with DNS to register client names; <strong>access
switches frequently do not</strong>. To populate DNS for wired servers using SLAAC,
operators need <strong>MAC and address visibility</strong> from switches (for example, via
Neighbor Discovery logging or sFlow/IPFIX) correlated with inventory to derive
hostnames. Ideally, selected <strong>Neighbor Discovery events</strong> would be exported to
a registration service --- a gap in many switch implementations.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="dhcpv6-and-hostname-registration"><name>DHCPv6 and Hostname Registration</name>
<t>Enterprises that distrust client self-registration prefer <strong>DHCPv6</strong> with
central lease logging. Clients <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> send <strong>DHCPv6 Option 39 (Client
FQDN)</strong> so the server can register forward and reverse DNS <xref target="RFC4704"></xref>
<xref target="RFC8415"></xref>. Support for Option 39 has varied by OS; operators <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>
verify current behavior on every deployed OS image (including macOS, Windows,
Linux, and container base images) rather than assuming parity.</t>
<t>Device-side <strong>Dynamic DNS updates</strong> remain possible but are often disabled in
enterprise policy. For why reverse zones matter during incidents, see
<xref target="network-diagnostics"></xref>.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="icmpv6-pmtud"><name>ICMPv6, PMTUD, and Middleboxes</name>

<section anchor="do-not-block-icmpv6"><name>Do Not Block ICMPv6</name>
<t>Teams trained to block ICMPv4 &quot;for security&quot; sometimes apply the same policy
to ICMPv6. <strong>ND and PMTUD depend on ICMPv6</strong> <xref target="RFC4443"></xref> <xref target="RFC8201"></xref>. Blocking
ICMPv6 produces hung connections, mysterious TLS timeouts, and DNS failures
that are misdiagnosed as application bugs. Filter <strong>specific message types</strong>
judiciously; do not implement blanket deny rules. For <strong>echo request/reply</strong>
used in reachability testing inside the data center, see <xref target="network-diagnostics"></xref>.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="path-mtu-discovery"><name>Path MTU Discovery</name>
<t>When many organizations enabled IPv6 on their web sites during <strong>World IPv6 Day</strong>
(2011) and <strong>World IPv6 Launch</strong> (2012), <strong>Path MTU Discovery failures</strong> forced
operators to <strong>lower TCP MSS</strong> on servers and load balancers until paths were
validated --- a reminder that IPv6 MTU assumptions differ from internal IPv4
MTU 1500 end-to-end paths. Mobile operators (for example, T-Mobile USA and
Reliance Jio in India) run <strong>IPv6-only</strong> access networks successfully at scale;
problems on enterprise fixed networks often come from <strong>middleboxes and
policy</strong>, not from IPv6 itself.</t>
<t>Hard PMTUD failures also interact with <strong>DNS over large responses</strong> when
fragmentation is mishandled. If fragmented UDP is dropped, DNS appears
&quot;flaky&quot; only for some records.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="vpns-and-nat64"><name>VPNs and NAT64</name>
<t>Some VPN products treat translated packets as attacks. <strong>NAT64</strong> <xref target="RFC6146"></xref>
changes headers; a VPN that validates packet integrity on IPv4 paths may <strong>drop
NAT64 flows</strong>. Prefer <strong>edge gateways</strong> for translation as described in
<xref target="internet-egress"></xref> and <xref target="ipv4-only-wrappers"></xref> rather than sprouting translators on
every host. Long-term, <strong>VPN endpoints should be native IPv6</strong> on the data
center side. Until then, document which access paths require IPv4 literal
connectivity vs IPv6.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="application-readiness"><name>Application and Software Readiness</name>
<t>IPv6 deployment exposes software that &quot;worked on the LAN&quot; only because the LAN
was IPv4. This section lists classes of problems seen in production data
centers and enterprise rollouts.</t>

<section anchor="enterprise-platform-inventory"><name>Enterprise Platform Inventory</name>
<t>Many enterprise platforms still assume IPv4-only access paths. Examples
reported in operator experience include <strong>Hadoop</strong>, certain <strong>object storage
APIs</strong>, <strong>Kubernetes</strong> dependencies (especially third-party charts and
sidecars), <strong>cloud firewalls</strong> (for example, Azure Firewall and third-party
NGFW images on cloud platforms where IPv6 support lagged vendor roadmaps), and
<strong>security analytics</strong> pipelines that ingest NetFlow or packet metadata on
IPv4 only.</t>
<t><strong>Action for SRE teams:</strong> maintain a <strong>living inventory</strong> of software in the
deployment path (data plane, control plane, CI/CD, security, logging) with an
explicit <strong>IPv6 supported / broken / untested</strong> classification. Monitoring
pipelines <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> continuously <strong>discover services not yet in that inventory</strong>
(see <xref target="observability"></xref>). Security research or monitoring that runs IPv4-only
cannot validate IPv6 attack surface; teams <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> require IPv6 parity before
accepting &quot;no IPv6 security issues&quot; claims.</t>
<t>This document does not attempt a canonical vendor matrix --- products change
--- but the inventory practice is mandatory for sane rollout planning.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="dev-environments"><name>Developer and Pre-Production Environments</name>
<t><strong>Provide dual-stack (and eventually IPv6-only) networks to developers as early
as possible</strong> --- ideally before production rollout, not after. Engineers who
code and debug only on IPv4-only laptops or lab VLANs ship software that
&quot;works in the office&quot; and fails when AAAA records appear in production.</t>
<t>It is customary to <strong>build and test new code in VMs or containers</strong> that mirror
production topology before release. Those evaluation environments <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>
include <strong>dual-stack</strong> and <strong>IPv6-only</strong> variants alongside legacy IPv4-only
images where brownfield support is still required. CI pipelines <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> run
integration tests against both address-family modes so a code push cannot
silently regress IPv6 without failing the build.</t>
<t>Platform teams <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> publish standard developer network profiles (dual-stack
lab, IPv6-only sandbox, simulated edge with NAT64) and document how to attach
local IDEs, test harnesses, and AI coding agents to them.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="hard-coded-addresses-and-localhost-pitfalls"><name>Hard-Coded Addresses and Localhost Pitfalls</name>
<t>A recurring defect is binding services to <strong><tt>127.0.0.1</tt></strong> instead of
<strong><tt>localhost</tt></strong> or <tt>::1</tt>. On dual-stack hosts, <tt>127.0.0.1</tt> listens <strong>IPv4
loopback only</strong>; IPv6 clients cannot connect even when the service &quot;runs
locally.&quot; The fix is to use name-based bind targets (<tt>localhost</tt>) or explicit
dual-stack sockets depending on platform API.</t>
<t>Similar bugs appear with <strong><tt>0.0.0.0</tt></strong> vs <strong><tt>::</tt></strong> listen semantics, health
probes that curl IPv4 literals, and container images that ship <tt>/etc/hosts</tt>
without IPv6 entries.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="ip-address-storage-in-application-data"><name>IP Address Storage in Application Data</name>
<t>Many services store client or server IP addresses in databases, logs, caches,
and message queues using <strong>fixed-width fields</strong> (32-bit integers, <tt>CHAR(15)</tt>)
or parsers that accept dotted decimal only. IPv6 requires <strong>structured address
types</strong> (128-bit binary, or text with adequate length) and family-aware
comparison.</t>
<t>Affected areas include:</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li><strong>Geolocation databases</strong> (for example, MaxMind and similar) used for
compliance, fraud, and ad targeting --- coverage and accuracy for IPv6 vary
widely.</li>
<li><strong>Real User Monitoring (RUM)</strong> and <strong>DNS steering</strong> products that map clients
to &quot;nearest&quot; PoP --- if the probe or edge logic is IPv4-only, steering
decisions silently degrade for IPv6 clients.</li>
<li><strong>Rate limiting and abuse detection</strong> keyed on &quot;IP&quot; strings with naive
splitting on <tt>.</tt> characters.</li>
</ul>
<t>Refactoring often touches every schema, serializer, and analytics job that
touched the field --- plan migration as a <strong>program</strong>, not a one-line fix.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="databases-acls-and-security-tools"><name>Databases, ACLs, and Security Tools</name>
<t><strong>MySQL and MariaDB</strong> host-based ACLs are historically <strong>string comparisons</strong>
on the client address field. IPv6 literals contain colons and zone identifiers;
copying IPv4 ACL patterns without testing produces false denials or overly
broad grants. Test <tt>USER@'2001:db8::/32'</tt>-style entries explicitly.</t>
<t>Security agents (EDR, IDS, WAF) may lack IPv6 decode paths even when they claim
dual-stack support. Validate <strong>both directions</strong> --- ingress to the service and
egress from the service --- under IPv6-only client paths. The same teams can
extend PR checks with static analysis rules (see <xref target="static-analysis"></xref>).</t>
</section>

<section anchor="language-runtimes"><name>Language Runtimes and Libraries</name>
<t><strong>Python</strong> exposes several <strong>deprecated socket helpers that are IPv4-only or
return only one address</strong>, yet remain common in production code and older
tutorials. Examples include:</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li><strong><tt>socket.gethostbyname()</tt></strong> and <strong><tt>socket.gethostbyname_ex()</tt></strong> --- resolve
a name to IPv4 only; use <strong><tt>socket.getaddrinfo()</tt></strong> and iterate all results
(see <xref target="name-resolution"></xref>).</li>
<li><strong><tt>socket.gethostbyaddr()</tt></strong> --- reverse lookup with IPv4-centric assumptions;
prefer <strong><tt>getnameinfo()</tt></strong> with a binary <tt>sockaddr</tt> from the connection.</li>
<li><strong><tt>socket.inet_aton()</tt></strong> and <strong><tt>socket.inet_ntoa()</tt></strong> --- convert IPv4
literals only; use <strong><tt>socket.inet_pton()</tt></strong> and <strong><tt>socket.inet_ntop()</tt></strong> for
both address families.</li>
</ul>
<t>These APIs <strong>will not return IPv6</strong> even when the host has AAAA records and
IPv6 connectivity. Replacing them is rarely a one-line change --- call sites,
tests, and error handling often assume 32-bit or dotted-decimal form.</t>
<t>Other languages have similar legacy (<tt>inet_aton</tt> assumptions, IPv4-only standard
library gaps). Code review checklists <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> include:</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li>No unparsed string IPs in business logic</li>
<li>Resolve names with a <strong>full-list</strong> API (see <xref target="name-resolution"></xref>); never call
legacy one-address helpers in new code</li>
<li>Tests that run against <strong>IPv6 literals and DNS names with AAAA records</strong></li>
</ul>
</section>

<section anchor="static-analysis"><name>Static Analysis and Pull Request Automation</name>
<t>Manual review does not scale across large monorepos. <strong>Security and platform
teams SHOULD integrate IPv6 readiness checks into pull request (PR) workflows</strong>,
piggybacking on existing gates rather than relying on a separate audit cycle.</t>

<section anchor="pattern-scanners-in-ci"><name>Pattern Scanners in CI</name>
<t>Ship <strong>Semgrep</strong>, <strong>CodeQL</strong>, or equivalent rules that flag likely IPv4-only
patterns, for example:</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li>Literal <tt>127.0.0.1</tt>, <tt>0.0.0.0</tt>, or dotted-decimal regexes used as addresses</li>
<li>Calls to deprecated Python socket helpers (see <xref target="language-runtimes"></xref>)</li>
<li><tt>AF_INET</tt> sockets where dual-stack or <tt>AF_INET6</tt> is required</li>
<li>Database columns or structs sized for IPv4-only (<tt>CHAR(15)</tt>, 32-bit integers)</li>
<li>String splits on <tt>.</tt> to parse &quot;IP addresses&quot;</li>
</ul>
<t>Security teams often own the rule pack; application teams own remediation.
Rules <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be published internally with examples and fix guidance.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="automated-remediation-pull-requests"><name>Automated Remediation Pull Requests</name>
<t>Beyond blocking merges, pipelines <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> open <strong>automatic PRs</strong> that propose
fixes when a scan finds matches on default branches or on a schedule. Some
findings are straightforward (replace <tt>gethostbyname</tt> with <tt>getaddrinfo</tt> usage);
others need context. <strong>AI-assisted patch generation</strong> can speed up bulk
refactors, but <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be reviewed by a human --- expect <strong>false positives</strong>
(for example, code that intentionally handles IPv4-only legacy clients).</t>
<t>Treat auto-generated PRs like any other contribution: tests, ownership by code
owners, and rollback plan.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="opt-out-annotations-for-engineers"><name>Opt-Out Annotations for Engineers</name>
<t>Engineers <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be able to <strong>suppress a finding on a specific line</strong> when
the IPv4-only behavior is intentional and documented --- for example, a
compatibility shim with a planned removal date. Define a <strong>codified comment</strong>
recognized by the scanner, placed <strong>immediately before</strong> the flagged line. An
example directive:</t>

<artwork><![CDATA[# ipv6-readiness: ignore-next-line -- see TICKET-123
]]></artwork>
<t>The project <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> document the exact directive string, required rationale
format, and whether ticket references are mandatory. Blanket disables of entire
files <bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14> be allowed without security team approval.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="ai-coding-agent-skills"><name>AI Coding Agent Skills</name>
<t>Many teams now use <strong>AI coding agents</strong> in the IDE and in CI. Add an <strong>IPv6
readiness skill</strong> (or equivalent project rule) to the agent environment --- and
<strong>push the same skill into application repositories</strong> --- so generated patches
default to <strong>dual-stack APIs</strong>, <strong><tt>getaddrinfo()</tt>-style resolution</strong>, and
IPv6-safe listen/bind patterns. The skill <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> require agents to verify
that new network code works when AAAA records are present and when IPv4 is
absent (IPv6-only paths). Treat this as part of the same program as Semgrep
and CodeQL rules, not a substitute for automated tests on dual-stack and
IPv6-only runners (see <xref target="dev-environments"></xref>).</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="documentation-examples"><name>Documentation and Presentations</name>
<t>Runbooks, architecture diagrams, wikis, training decks, and conference slides
<strong>SHOULD use IPv6 addresses in examples by default</strong>, unless the example is
inherently IPv4-specific. Using IPv4-only literals in internal documentation
normalizes the wrong protocol for new engineers and hides gaps until production
rollout. IETF documents follow the same principle: examples <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> use IPv6
and reserved documentation prefixes rather than arbitrary or production
addresses <xref target="RFC3849"></xref> <xref target="RFC5737"></xref>.</t>
<t>When an example needs an IP address or prefix, follow <strong>IETF documentation
address rules</strong>:</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li><strong>IPv6 (preferred):</strong> use the documentation prefixes reserved in <xref target="RFC3849"></xref>
(<tt>2001:db8::/32</tt>) and <xref target="RFC9637"></xref> (<tt>3fff::/20</tt> for larger or more realistic
layouts). Represent addresses in <strong>canonical text form</strong> per <xref target="RFC5952"></xref>
(lowercase hex, suppress leading zeros, use <tt>::</tt> compression).</li>
<li><strong>IPv4 (only when required):</strong> use the TEST-NET blocks in <xref target="RFC5737"></xref>
(<tt>192.0.2.0/24</tt>, <tt>198.51.100.0/24</tt>, <tt>203.0.113.0/24</tt>) --- not production
space, arbitrary <tt>10.0.0.0/8</tt> lab subnets, or other unreserved ranges that
could collide with real deployments.</li>
<li><strong>Names:</strong> use example domain names from <xref target="RFC2606"></xref> (<tt>example.com</tt>,
<tt>example.net</tt>, <tt>example.org</tt>) rather than real operator domains.</li>
</ul>
<t>Review documentation the same way code is reviewed: a slide full of <tt>10.x.x.x</tt>
or <tt>192.168.x.x</tt> examples teaches habits that conflict with IPv6-first data
center operation. Prefer <tt>2001:db8:...</tt> and service names unless the document
explicitly covers legacy IPv4 behavior.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="name-resolution"><name>Resolving Hostnames to Addresses</name>
<t>This section covers name-to-address APIs and client resolution behavior --- the
connection layer above application readiness gaps cataloged above.</t>
<t>Turning a hostname into addresses is a separate step from choosing which
address to connect to. Application code <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> use an API that returns <strong>all</strong>
candidate addresses, then apply local policy (retries, Happy Eyeballs
<xref target="RFC8305"></xref>, load spreading --- see <xref target="address-selection"></xref> and
<xref target="client-load-balancing"></xref>). When implementing Happy Eyeballs, <strong>delay the IPv4
connection attempt</strong> so IPv6 has more time to succeed first --- a late start for
IPv4 is consistent with <xref target="RFC8305"></xref> and reduces accidental IPv4-first behavior
on dual-stack paths.</t>

<section anchor="use-getaddrinfo-not-legacy-one-address-apis"><name>Use getaddrinfo(), Not Legacy One-Address APIs</name>
<t>On POSIX systems the correct resolver entry point is <strong><tt>getaddrinfo()</tt></strong>
<xref target="RFC3493"></xref>. It takes a hostname (or numeric address string), service/port hints,
and an <tt>addrinfo</tt> hints structure, and returns a <strong>linked list of <tt>addrinfo</tt>
structures</strong> --- one node per address. The caller <strong>MUST iterate the entire
list</strong> (the <tt>ai_next</tt> chain), copy each <tt>sockaddr</tt> into binary form (see
<xref target="address-representation"></xref>), and <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> release the list with <tt>freeaddrinfo()</tt>.</t>
<t>Please note: <strong><tt>getaddrinfo()</tt></strong> is the name-to-address API for retrieving a
full list; it is not the same as:</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li><strong><tt>gethostbyname()</tt></strong> and <strong><tt>gethostbyname2()</tt></strong> --- deprecated, not
thread-safe, and still present in old tutorials. Many call sites use only the
first address even when multiple are available.</li>
<li><strong><tt>inet_addr()</tt></strong>, <strong><tt>inet_aton()</tt></strong>, and <strong><tt>inet_pton()</tt></strong> --- parse a
<strong>literal</strong> address string into binary; they perform <strong>no DNS lookup</strong> and
return a single address only.</li>
<li>Higher-level HTTP or RPC helpers that resolve a name internally and connect to
<strong>one</strong> chosen address without exposing the full set --- fine for quick
clients, unsuitable when the service relies on multiple A/AAAA records.</li>
</ul>
<t>To request both IPv4 and IPv6 results, set <tt>hints.ai_family</tt> to <tt>AF_UNSPEC</tt>
(unless a deliberate single-family policy applies). Inspect <tt>ai_family</tt>,
<tt>ai_addrlen</tt>, and <tt>ai_addr</tt> on <strong>each</strong> list element; do not assume every node
has the same address family.</t>
<t>Language runtimes expose the same idea under different names:</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li><strong>Python:</strong> <tt>socket.getaddrinfo()</tt> returns a list of tuples --- iterate all
entries; avoid <tt>socket.gethostbyname()</tt>, which returns one IPv4 address.</li>
<li><strong>Go:</strong> <tt>net.DefaultResolver.LookupIPAddr()</tt> or <tt>LookupIP()</tt>; avoid code paths
that stop after the first returned address.</li>
<li><strong>Java:</strong> <tt>InetAddress.getAllByName()</tt> returns an array; <strong><tt>getByName()</tt></strong>
returns only the first address and is a common source of &quot;works in the lab&quot;
failures under round-robin DNS.</li>
<li><strong>Node.js:</strong> <tt>dns.promises.resolve()</tt> or <tt>dns.lookup()</tt> with <tt>{ all: true }</tt>;
the default <tt>lookup()</tt> without <tt>all: true</tt> returns a single address.</li>
</ul>
<t>Pay special attention when connecting to a <strong>hostname</strong> (as opposed to a numeric
literal): resolution can return both IPv4 and IPv6 addresses, and often more than
one of each. A failed <tt>connect()</tt> to <strong>one</strong> of those addresses does <strong>not</strong>
mean the host is unreachable. Application code <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> report the
destination as down after trying only the first AAAA or A record and never
the other family, or after IPv4 fails while unused IPv6 candidates remain (and
vice versa). Try other addresses from the resolved list --- or use Happy Eyeballs
<xref target="RFC8305"></xref> --- before concluding that the service cannot be reached.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="why-the-full-list-matters"><name>Why the Full List Matters</name>
<t>DNS often publishes <strong>multiple A and AAAA records</strong> for availability and load
distribution. Connecting to <tt>result-&gt;ai_addr</tt> and ignoring <tt>ai_next</tt> defeats
that design. After collecting the list, the application (or a shared library)
chooses order: IPv6-first, Happy Eyeballs, random shuffle within a family, or
explicit retry on failure. <strong><tt>getaddrinfo()</tt> supplies candidates; it does not
replace client-side load balancing.</strong></t>
<t>Note that libc implementations may <strong>reorder</strong> the list per <xref target="RFC6724"></xref> before
returning it (see <xref target="address-selection"></xref>). You still need every element --- reorder
yourself if policy requires --- but you cannot skip resolution and hope DNS
order survives unchanged.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="numeric-input-at-the-edge"><name>Numeric Input at the Edge</name>
<t>When configuration or user input contains an address <strong>literal</strong> rather than a
hostname, <strong><tt>inet_pton()</tt></strong> (or the language equivalent) converts it to binary
for storage. When input might be either a name or a literal, <strong><tt>getaddrinfo()</tt></strong>
accepts both; alternatively, try literal parse first, then fall back to DNS.
Either way, convert once to binary and use binary forms internally.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="address-selection"><name>Address Selection, gai.conf, and DNS Round Robin</name>
<t>The Linux file <tt>/etc/gai.conf</tt> and the algorithms in <xref target="RFC6724"></xref> control
<strong>address selection order</strong> for dual-stack hosts --- which address family and
which destination address are tried first. This is invisible in application
source but visible in production load distribution.</t>
<t><strong>RFC 6724 destination address selection Rule 9</strong> (&quot;Use longest matching
prefix&quot;) compares each candidate destination with its likely source address
and <strong>sorts addresses deterministically</strong> <xref target="RFC6724"></xref>. Resolver libraries such
as <strong>glibc</strong> implement this sorting inside <tt>getaddrinfo()</tt>. The effect:
<strong>DNS round-robin is not a load-balancing strategy on IPv6</strong> (and is weakened
on IPv4 in many cases). A round-robin AAAA record can collapse to &quot;always try
the same address first&quot; once Rule 9 runs, concentrating connections on one
backend. The problem is subtle on IPv4 but <strong>often severe on IPv6</strong>.</t>
<t>Rule 9 is reasonable on the global Internet but <strong>often wrong inside a data
center</strong>, where many servers are functionally declared equidistant and
operators expect DNS or
anycast to spread load. Mitigations include:</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li>Perform <strong>client-side load balancing</strong> in the application or library.</li>
<li>Fetch all addresses (for example, via <tt>getaddrinfo()</tt> without premature
sorting, or via a resolver that preserves DNS order), then choose randomly
<strong>within the same address family</strong> --- do not shuffle v4 and v6 together in
ways that accidentally defeat IPv6 preference policy.</li>
<li>Use service meshes, anycast, or explicit endpoint lists rather than naive
round-robin alone.</li>
</ul>
<t>Changing <tt>/etc/gai.conf</tt> adjusts precedence tables but <strong>does not fully
disable Rule 9</strong> in all implementations. Treat load balancing as a <strong>software
concern</strong>, not something DNS alone provides.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="runtime-resolution"><name>Runtime-Specific Resolution (Not Always glibc)</name>
<t>Examples above assume POSIX <strong><tt>getaddrinfo()</tt></strong> via <strong>glibc</strong> (or an equivalent
libc). Not every language or runtime uses libc for name resolution. <strong>Java</strong>
maintains its own resolver stack and system properties such as
<strong><tt>java.net.preferIPv4Stack</tt></strong> and <strong><tt>java.net.preferIPv6Addresses</tt></strong> that
override address-family preference independently of <tt>/etc/gai.conf</tt>. A JVM
configured to prefer IPv4 can appear &quot;IPv6 broken&quot; even when the OS resolver
returns AAAA records. Test Java services with explicit property settings and
with <strong><tt>InetAddress.getAllByName()</tt></strong>, not <strong><tt>getByName()</tt></strong>.</t>
<t>In extreme cases, an <strong><tt>/etc/resolv.conf</tt></strong> that lists <strong>only IPv6 nameserver
addresses</strong> can interact badly with runtimes that bootstrap DNS over IPv4 first
or assume a v4-reachable resolver path. Symptoms include slow resolution,
timeouts, or unexpected family ordering. Qualify resolver configuration on
dual-stack and IPv6-only hosts for each runtime in the fleet, not only for C
callers of <tt>getaddrinfo()</tt>.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="client-load-balancing"><name>Client-Side Load Balancing</name>
<t>Client-side load balancing builds on the resolution patterns in <xref target="name-resolution"></xref>
when services publish multiple A/AAAA records.</t>
<t>As described in <xref target="address-selection"></xref>, <strong>RFC 6724 Rule 9</strong> reorders addresses
returned from DNS. In data centers that rely on multiple AAAA records for
spread, connection counts can skew badly --- one backend receives most IPv6
connections while others appear idle. This section assumes the application has
already obtained the <strong>full address list</strong> using the patterns in
<xref target="name-resolution"></xref>.</t>
<t><strong>Recommended pattern:</strong></t>

<ol spacing="compact">
<li>Resolve the service name to all addresses.</li>
<li>Partition addresses by address family.</li>
<li>Apply family preference policy (operator choice: IPv6-first, happy eyeballs,
or parallel). For Happy Eyeballs, <strong>start IPv4 attempts after a deliberate
delay</strong> so IPv6 connections have priority time to complete.</li>
<li><strong>Randomize or round-robin within each family</strong> rather than trusting DNS
order after <tt>getaddrinfo()</tt>.</li>
<li>Optionally implement retries across the full set on failure.</li>
</ol>
<t>Implement load balancing in <strong>shared client libraries</strong> so every service does
not rediscover the same RFC 6724 interaction.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="network-diagnostics"><name>Network Diagnostics in the Data Center</name>
<t>A data center is a <strong>closed, operator-controlled environment</strong>. Two practices
that help SREs diagnose routing, DNS, and reachability problems on <strong>both IPv4
and IPv6</strong> are often skipped because they feel optional or risky.</t>

<section anchor="reverse-dns"><name>Reverse DNS</name>
<t>Maintain <strong>forward and reverse DNS</strong> for long-lived infrastructure: servers,
load balancers, management interfaces, and other addresses that appear in logs,
firewall hits, flow records, and packet captures. Reverse zones (<strong>PTR</strong> for
IPv4, <strong>ip6.arpa</strong> for IPv6 <xref target="RFC3596"></xref>) map an address back to a hostname.
That mapping is routine on IPv4 but becomes <strong>essential on IPv6</strong>, where
prefixes are not human-scannable and incidents otherwise devolve into comparing
128-bit literals. Reverse records <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be created in the same change
workflow as forward records and IPAM assignments (see <xref target="dns-registration"></xref>).
Spot-check with <tt>dig -x</tt> or equivalent on both address families before relying
on reverse lookup during an outage.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="controlled-icmp-echo-ping"><name>Controlled ICMP Echo (Ping)</name>
<t>Teams trained to drop <strong>ICMP echo request/reply</strong> (&quot;ping&quot;) on the public Internet
sometimes apply the same rule everywhere. <strong>Inside the data center</strong>, allowing
echo request/reply <strong>with limits</strong> --- rate limits, scoped ACLs, source
restrictions to management networks or jump hosts, or equivalent controls --- is
<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14> for troubleshooting. A successful or failed ping quickly
separates &quot;no route&quot; from &quot;route but service down&quot; on both IPv4 and IPv6 without
opening application ports.</t>
<t>This is separate from the ICMPv6 requirements in <xref target="icmpv6-pmtud"></xref>: Neighbor
Discovery and Path MTU Discovery need specific ICMPv6 types on production paths
and <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be blocked wholesale. Controlled echo is an additional
<strong>diagnostic convenience</strong> on top of that baseline. Operators <bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>
replace protocol-required ICMP with echo-only rules, nor block echo in ways that
remove a basic reachability tool from on-call engineers. Apply the same
philosophy to <strong>ICMPv4 echo</strong> inside the fabric: constrain abuse, but preserve
a controlled way to test L3 connectivity during incidents.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="security-considerations"><name>Security Considerations</name>
<t>IPv6 restores global routability; <strong>absence of NAT is not absence of need for
firewall policy</strong>. ULAs and link-local addresses still require filtering at
boundaries. ICMPv6 filtering must preserve ND and PMTUD. Application-level
ACLs and security products must parse IPv6 literals correctly (see
<xref target="application-readiness"></xref>).</t>
<t><strong>Security appliances and host security software are notoriously weak on IPv6</strong>
--- incomplete decode, IPv4-only dashboards, agents that drop or mislabel v6
traffic, and policies that silently fail open or closed. Engage the <strong>security
organization very early</strong> in the IPv6 program, in parallel with out-of-band and
network design (see <xref target="oob-management"></xref>). In many enterprises, application SREs
<strong>do not have full visibility</strong> into which tools the security team deploys;
there is often deliberate <strong>operational secrecy</strong> around EDR, NDR, DLP, and
forensics platforms. Assume unknown agents exist on every host until proven
otherwise (see <xref target="host-agents"></xref>); establish a shared readiness process with
security leadership rather than discovering blockers during the first IPv6-only
pilot.</t>
<t>Security monitoring systems <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> receive IPv6 traffic mirrors, tap coverage,
and metadata <strong>on parity with IPv4</strong> before declaring IPv6 production-ready.
Validate that incident response playbooks (pcap collection, IP blocking,
geo blocking, threat intel feeds) work with <strong>128-bit addresses</strong> and canonical
text forms <xref target="RFC5952"></xref>. PR static analysis for IPv4-only patterns
(see <xref target="static-analysis"></xref>) complements but does not replace security-tool
qualification.</t>
<t>Operator inventory practices in <xref target="application-readiness"></xref> also reduce supply-chain
risk from undeclared IPv4-only dependencies in the control plane.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="iana-considerations"><name>IANA Considerations</name>
<t>This document has no IANA actions.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="acknowledgments"><name>Acknowledgments</name>
<t>The authors thank the following people who contributed suggestions and
editorial improvements to this document:</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li><strong>Jason Healy</strong> (Suffield Academy)</li>
</ul>
</section>

</middle>

<back>
<references><name>Normative References</name>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1918.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3493.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3596.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3849.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4193.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4291.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4443.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4704.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4861.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4890.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5737.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5952.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6146.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6724.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6890.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8200.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8201.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8415.xml"/>
</references>
<references><name>Informative References</name>
<reference anchor="ARCEP-IPV6-GUIDE" target="https://www.arcep.fr/fileadmin/cru-1648459125/reprise/observatoire/ipv6/guide-entreprises-how-to-deploy-IPv6-march-2022.pdf">
  <front>
    <title>How to Deploy IPv6 in Your Enterprise (Guide for Enterprises)</title>
    <author>
      <organization>ARCEP</organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2022" month="March"></date>
  </front>
</reference>
<reference anchor="ARIN-APPS-V6" target="https://www.arin.net/resources/guide/ipv6/preparing_apps_for_v6.pdf">
  <front>
    <title>Preparing Applications for IPv6: A Software Developers Guide to Writing and Migrating Networked Applications for Use on IPv6 Networks</title>
    <author>
      <organization>ARIN</organization>
    </author>
  </front>
</reference>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2606.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4038.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7381.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8305.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9637.xml"/>
</references>

</back>

</rfc>
